Okay, so let us consider a few more
examples of this idea of going
from Haskell code to Prolog code.
Because then we can use the predicates in
Prolog and as you have just seen, we can also
use them in rather different ways
than just as a forward function.
But let's not actually execute the programs
now, let's just see how this translation,
transfer of code from Haskell to
Prolog can work for certain functions.
Okay, and to remind you, so the base
idea of this translation was that
if in Haskell, well, in order to avoid
nested function calls in Haskell.
Yeah,
so to avoid nested function calls,
because those we can't have in Prolog.
Because we don't write down
nested expressions but rather just
predicate applications, literals that
occur in rules, facts, and queries.
So, there was this basic idea of if
you have something like 'f (g x y) z'.
So, a nested function call
of a function which has
an argument that has another
function call nested.
And the idea is that
is basically on the Haskell side interpreted as
something like for a new variable 'z', let's say.
Let’s write this line we've
written in Haskell, maybe.
So, the local definition for the 'u',
namely, saying that it would be 'u = g x y'.
And now since we have things that are not
nested function calls, they can be very directly
transliterated to something on the Prolog side, okay?
That's what happened on the previous
slide, in the previous video.
Okay, let's do it for an additional function.
Okay, let's do it for some other functions.
So, let's look at the 'length' function.
Yes, so on the extra side, 'length'
is very simply defined as saying that
the length of the empty list is 0.
And the length of the non-empty list is what?
The pattern-matching on the
non-empty list, and then what?
Well, that is the length of the rest list + 1.
And of course, this is also a
nested function call here, right?
So, I mean, you don't necessarily have to write
these brackets and that is because of parsing rules,
but this is really a nested function call.
Where the outer function is the '+',
and the inner function is the 'length'.
So, it fits the pattern above, we couldn't
directly write something like this in Prolog, okay?
What can we do, however?
Well, the first line is one that very directly
lends itself to be written
as a binary predicate, right?
Because it has two constants.
The empty list as one constant
and zero as the result constant.
So, this in Prolog would
simply be written like this.
Simply say, it is true as a fact that the
length of the empty list is zero, right?
Written as a fact, okay?
Now what about the other rules
where we just said we would have to
interpret this as something
without a nested function call.
So, the reasonable way would be to say, the -.
First, we formulate this as let’s say,
m + 1 where m is the length of xs.
And the benefit of this is that 'length xs'
equals m can be written in this style, right?
Just as a binary predicate.
The binary predicate 'length'
applied to the list and its length.
That's the idea.
So, after you have done this, how
can we rewrite the definition?
Well, we can then on the Prolog side write
something like it is the case that the
length of such a list, and of course, we have to
rewrite it as Prolog style list pattern, right?
Which was not with this colon as a cons
constructor, but instead with a vertical bar
in square brackets.
And also, we have to rewrite the
variables in uppercase, you know to fix
or fit to Prolog's syntactic guidelines.
So, this would be written as X
for the head, XS for the rest.
So, this would be the input side.
And for the output side, well
let’s think about this 'm + 1'.
So, let's, for the moment, do this symbolically.
So, if this original idea
that was also used for the 'add' predicate that
we don’t write extra numbers two, three, etc.
but something like; SS0
for the number two, right?
So, let's express this +1 with
the successor constructor.
So, then we would here write that
the length of this is 'm + 1'.
So, the successor of some
variable 'M', given that, right?
So, we need this precondition, given
that the length of Xs is M, okay?
So, if the length of Xs is M then
the length of something prefixed -.
So, one element prefixed in front of
Xs, the length of that is s(M), okay?
So, that would be a reasonable definition
of length in Prolog as a predicate.
And then we could also actually start
asking right now if we have a predicate
for length instead of a function. What
about using it in a fashion where we
give this instantiation a value for
the length and ask about the list?
Which is not possible in Haskell, of course,
because it only works forwards with functions.
Okay, so this was the length function
now turned into a Prolog predicate.
Let’s do some further examples.
So, another typical list processing function in
Haskell would be, of course, the 'list append'.
So, the '++' operator.
Which we won’t use in this operator
syntax, but as a ternary predicate.
So, let’s remember what the definition and also
syntax actually on the Haskell side will be.
It is a polymorphic function and, of course,
we won’t write down this type in Prolog because
Prolog is not typed, but on the Haskell side
we would have this as a polymorphic function.
And then it would be defined by saying that,
the empty list plus whatever is that whatever,
and the non-empty list appended
with another list is what?
Well, the definition actually
is, it is x in front of whatever
is the appending of xs and ys, okay?
That should make sense.
Okay, again, of course, we won't be able to
translate this directly to the Prolog side. Why?
Well, mainly because of
this nested function, right?
This is a function call which
produces some list which is then
combined with another element to
produce the final output list.
So, that's a nested function call which we
can’t have in this form on the Prolog side.
So, what would this correspond to
according to the same idea as here?
Well, you would have to rename the
subexpression, which is another function call.
So, actually, we could
rewrite on the Haskell side
by saying: Well, this is actually x in front of zs,
where we compute zs as the 'append' of xs and ys.
And the idea is again that if we
have a ternary predicate for append,
then this, with just variables
and no nested function calls,
can be written as a literal like we
did for 'length' up here, for example.
Okay, so what do we have to
do on the Prolog side then?
Well, as I said, we won't use an operator like
this. Rather, we will use a named predicate.
So, let's call it 'append'.
And while we can’t write down the type, we can at
least write down that it is a ternary predicate.
Syntax was also mentioned on slides that
sometimes, for documentation purposes for
example, we at least write down
the arity of a predicate in Prolog.
Also, because the same predicate
name can use a different arity,
so, it’s helpful to have that information.
And then what are the rules?
Well, their first rule is just a
fact and should be very simple.
Yes, it’s stating something about three
things; the constant empty list and then
twice the same variable list.
So, that translates directly to
a rule which is simply just a fact and not
a rule because that’s not preconditioned.
Something like this.
So, the empty list appended with
something is that something, a fact, okay?
And what about the second line?
Well, now we are already a bit more
comfortable maybe with the different
list syntax or this translates on the Prolog
side into this syntax as the square brackets,
then X | and the name of the rest list.
This is again just a variable
just to be written in uppercase.
And then what should be the outcome?
Well, on the output side we
want to have a list again.
So, it's also a list pattern
with head X and some rest
which previously was a nested function call,
but now we have replaced it with a variable.
So, actually, we want to express
this, which is just this pattern.
And of course, this holds only under
certain preconditions which introduce
these Zs basically because we
still need to express this.
And what is this saying?
It is saying that the appending
of Xs and Ys should be Zs.
So, here we would have as a precondition for
our ternary predicate that the appending of Xs
and Ys is Zs.
And that is the translation of the above
Haskell function to the Prolog side.
And again, with this, we could do things
we can in Haskell, like providing two
input lists and asking for the output list.
But we could do other queries.
For example, we could give the output
list and ask for all pairs of lists
which appended give that output list.
That's not something we can do on the Haskell
side because you can't run this backwards.
But for such a predicate, we can
essentially run backwards, okay?
And let me make a third example
which isn't a recursive example but
illustrates the pattern-match syntax again.
So, let's look at a very simple function for a
second on the Haskell side, which essentially
given any list is supposed to return
the second element, and we don't want
to do this with list indexing or something
like that, but simply with pattern-match.
So, how could this be
expressed on the Haskell side?
We are going to write something like this.
Yes, say we have a non-empty list, so it’s
something in front of something; if the first
something doesn’t matter to us, we don’t care
because we want to have the second thing.
So, we use an anonymous variable here,
then we have some element that we are
interested in, so we have to name it.
And then there must be some rest, but that
is again something we don’t care about.
It must be there because we need
a list of at least two elements in
order to access the second element.
So, there must be some rest list.
It could be the empty list,
something, and we don't care about it.
So, we use the anonymous variable pattern, and
well, the outcome would be simply X, okay?
That's on the Haskell side.
There is no nested function call now, so we don't
need to apply something like this trick here.
Nevertheless, we want to see how
this looks on the Prolog side.
Now that is more an issue of how
to use this different list syntax.
So, what we want is, of course,
a binary predicate, right?
Because it's a function with
one argument, one result.
On the Prolog side, the
predicate should be binary
to have places both for the
input and for the output.
And what would?
Well, there would be only
one rule, which is a fact.
Because there is no
precondition or recursive calls.
So, what could that fact look like?
Well, on the left, we have the
Prolog version of this pattern.
And what is the Prolog version of this pattern?
Well, the syntax could be something like this.
So, we don't care about the first
thing; then we have a rest list
of which we know that the
head element would be X.
And then there is another rest
list about which we do not care.
Yes, so this would be a translation of this.
A translation of this Haskell pattern.
And then we say: Well, the output is X.
This could be a fact that
represents the above line.
Or now in Prolog are actually more
different ways of writing this.
That was also already mentioned
on one of the syntax slides.
For example, this could also
have been written as saying:
We want to have a list; we don’t
care about the first element,
we care about the second element; it should be
the variable X or matched/bound to the variable X.
And then there is some rest we don't care about.
And this is related to X by this predicate.
Or another version would be to
use the '.' as the constructor
for basically the cons constructor from Haskell.
Then this would be written as
this pattern for binary '.'
with the first element of the list.
That is something we don't really care about,
and there is a rest list which is again
constructed with the data constructor, and the
first element is the X we are interested in.
And then, there is again some
unknown and not cared about rest.
Then I have to match up the brackets.
This could also be written like that.
And probably there are some other
ways you could think of writing this.
For example, you could replace
this with this pattern again.
Okay, these are equivalent ways; it’s just very
important once you start writing predicates on lists
to get a bit comfortable with this.
Yes, on the Haskell side, there are also
different ways to find this, of course, right?
So, there are also literal patterns that
you can write in function definitions.
Okay, but let's not focus
on Haskell now; let’s just
appreciate and consider these different
ways of writing this in Prolog.
Okay, that’s it for these examples.